Guide to the Origin Archive 1951-1968 MSS 021 MSS.021
Fales Library and Special Collections
Origin Archive
1951-1968
Fales Library and Special Collections
Origin (Boston, Mass.)
MSS.021
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Origin was a small avant garde literary magazine that was published from 1951 to 1985. The Origin Archive consists of correspondence and manuscripts that were sent to its editor, Cid Corman, for the first 17 years of the magazine's existence.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical/Biographical Note:
Origin was a small avant garde literary magazine that was published from 1951 until 1985. Its editor, Cid Coreman, was a poet, writer and translator. In 1948, he endeavored to establish a "poetic community" and organized poetry events at public libraries around Boston as well as poetry readings on the radio. In the midst of this activity, in 1951, Corman started Origin which featured his works and other emerging poets of the day, including: Carol Berge´, Robert Creeley, Theodore Enslin, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Gary Snyder, Denise Levertov, Louis Zukofsky, Paul Blackburn, William Bronk, and Charles Olson, among many others. In the late 1950's, Corman moved to Japan where he continued to write and began translating works of Japanese poetry. He has also translated works from Italian and French. He now lives in Kyoto, Japan.
Sources:
Arnold, Bob and Susan. "Cid Coreman and Origin Press." Longhouse publishers and Booksellers. 22 Jan. 2003. [http://www.longhousepoetry.com/corman.html]
Cid Corman, Papers, 1942-76 [finding aid]. Kent State University Libraries. 30 January 2003 [http://speccoll.library.kent.edu/].
Scope and Content Note
The Origin Archive is a part of the Avant Garde Collection at the Fales Library, New York University. The Fales Library is the primary special collections division of the NYU libraries, housing nearly 200,000 volumes of English and American literature from 1700 to the present. Strengths of the collection include the development of the English and American novel, with an emphasis on the Gothic and the Victorian novel.
The Origin Archive consists of the correspondence received by Cid Corman concerning the avant garde journal Origin. The collection comprises original manuscripts from: Carol Berge´, Robert Creeley, Theodore Enslin, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Denise Levertov, and Gary Snyder. Copies of Origin are not part of this archive but are available to view at the Fales Library.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into one series.
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
American poetry -- 20th century.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; American literature -- 20th century.; Avant-garde (Aesthetics); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Postcards.; Literature, Experimental.; Boston (Mass.) |x Intellectual life |y 20th century.; Small presses.; National Poetry Foundation (U.S.); Enslin, Theodore; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Origin (Boston, Mass.); Avison, Margaret; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence; Corman, Cid; Blackburn, Paul; Levertov, Denise, 1923-1997; Bergé, Carol, 1928-
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Allen, Donald, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Avison, Margaret, 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barker, Richard, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Berge´, Carol, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blackburn, Paul, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Enslin, Theodore, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Enslin, Theodore, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Enslin, Theodore, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ferlinghetti, Lawrence, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hentoff, Nat., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hirschman, Jack, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Kitasono, Katue, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Levertov, Denise, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Logan, John, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Randall, Margaret, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Risi, Nelo, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Rothenberg, Jerome, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Scholl, Albert Arnold, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Snyder, Gary, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sorrentino, Gilbert, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Weiss, Theodore, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Williams, Jonathan, 1953-1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)